{
  "reference_number": "12396",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "It should be able to be accelerated but not weakened. If political parties can run on winding iyt back then all sorts of stalling and\n minimising could be encouraged."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "unsure how much flexibility is ideal; trade-off between predictability and agility...?"
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "This could be useful. For example the Bill could set out reducing per capital private vehicle kilometres travelled for NZTA and regional\n transport agencies and authorities to achieve in their transport and land use budgets and plans."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "NZTA, AT, MoT, local authorities and all other transport and land use powers. As above, a key area to work with in the transition to a\n post carbon economy is transport. Here public agencies and authorities have a huge influence, and firm targets should be set to\n guide them to invest in the best way to accelerate the transition. Going post carbon must be the third key priority after safety and\n\n access."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I see advantages in the Commission being separate and making binding decisions. It is important to try to make this as a-patry\n\npolitical as possible. Ideally all sides of the House should have a role in setting it up and have buy in as it needs to be consistent way\nbeyond any election cycle."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Makes decisions itself in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 10,
      "notes": "see above."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "But also consider adding agriculture and transport specialists...?"
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Maybe. Difficult question; would that a) add to its work load, and b) confuse its aims from purely reducing harm? Though adaptaion\nwill become increasingly necessary regardless of success in reducing emissions."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    }
  ]
}
